Register of the Samuel Irving Katz papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Samuel Irving Katz papers
1937-1995
2000C7
Katz, Samuel Irving, 1916-
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (1.6 linear feet)
Biographical data, speeches and writings, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to international finance and to operations of the Federal Reserve Board.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is arranged in 6 series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Speeches and writings, Career file, Printed matter, and Oversize materials. The speeches and writings were originally arranged separately as "lectures and speeches to U.S. and international organizations and institutions" and "analytic papers, studies."
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Samuel I. Katz papers, University Archives, Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Biographical Note
1916 Born, Nashville, Tennessee
1935-1948 Agricultural economist, United States Department of Agriculture
1940 Received bachelor of arts degree, George Washington University
1942 Received master of arts degree, George Washington University
1943-1946 First Lieutenant, Economic Division, United States Military Government for Germany, United States Army
1948 Received master in public administration degree, Harvard University
1948-1974 Advisor, Division of International Finance, United States Federal Reserve Board
1958-1965 Lecturer, American University
1966-1968 Professorial lecturer, George Washington University
1969 Visiting professor, Sloan School of Management, Massachusetts Institute of Technology (M.I.T.)
1974- Professor, Georgetown University
1974-1986 Director, Georgetown University's Bankers Forum
1977-1982 Editor, Finance and Development, publication of the International Monetary Fund and World Bank
1979 Editor, U.S.-European Monetary Relations
1993 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers document the life and career of American economist Samuel Irving Katz through biographical materials, speeches and writings, correspondence, and printed matter related to international finance and to operations of the Federal Reserve Board.
Katz was an expert on international monetary relations, especially in the area of European monetary problems. The Speeches and writings include typescripts and printed copies concerning economic topics, including exchange rates.
The Career file contains materials related to various positions Katz held throughout his career. From 1943 to 1946, Katz served with the United States Army, working with the postwar military government in Germany on issues of price controls. From 1948 to 1974, Katz was an economist with the Federal Reserve Board. The collection includes materials from a study concerning Great Britain, which Katz was involved with during the late 1950s. In addition to his work with the Federal Reserve, Katz taught at Georgetown University, Harvard University, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Tufts University. The file includes course lecture outlines and materials on the Georgetown University Bankers Forum, a program which Katz directed from 1974 to 1982. Additional information on Katz's career can be found in the Biographical file, which includes his curriculum vitae.
United States. Federal Reserve Board.; Economists.; International finance.; United States--Economic policy.
- Biographical file, 1937-1995 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes clippings, curriculum vitae, military records, and memorials.
  - General, 1995 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings, 1977, 1993 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Curriculum vitae and biographical information, 1937-1992 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Memorial file, 1993 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Military file, 1942-1947 (Folder 1: 5)
    See also career file
- Correspondence, 1961-1987 (Box 1)
  Includes correspondence with economists and bankers.
  - Acheson, Edward Campion, 1961 (Folder 1: 6)
    Includes photograph
  - Guth, Wilfred, 1975 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Meade, James, 1987 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Stem, Carl H., 1978 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Watt, David, 1975-1978 (Folder 1: 10)
    Includes letters from Charles Olsen and Keith Kyle
- Speeches and writings, 1953-1992 (Box 1-2)
  Contains typescripts and printed copies of speeches and writings on economics.
  - Bibliographies, undated (Folder 1: 11)
  - Unidentified typescript, undated (Folder 1: 12)
    Section titles include "Three Approaches to International Monetary Reform," "The Pure-Gold Approach," "The Unconditional-Liquidity Approach," "The Conditional Liquidity Approach," "The SDR and Fund Reform," "Symmetry Proposals: The Pre-Bretton Woods Period," and "Symmetry Proposals: The Post-1960 Period"
  - "Exchange Rates and Balance-of-Payments Adjustment: The Post-1945 Experience, undated (Folder 1: 13)
  - "How Forward Exchange Market Works,", undated (Folder 1: 14)
  - Paul A. Volcker, degree citation, undated (Folder 1: 15)
  - "The Canadian Dollar: A Fluctuating Currency,", 1953 (Folder 1: 16)
  - "Leads and Lags in Sterling Payments,", 1953 (Folder 1: 17)
  - "The Future of Sterling,", 1955 (Folder 1: 18)
  - "Le dollar canadien et le cours de change fluctuant,", 1955 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Sterling's Recurring Postwar Payments Crises,", 1955 (Folder 1: 20)
  - "The Post-War Growth of Consumer Instalment Credit in the United Kingdom Summary,", 1957 (Folder 1: 21)
  - "Radcliffe Report: Monetary Policy and Debt-Management Reconciled?,", 1960 (Folder 1: 22)
  - "Britain 1961: The Basle Credits and the Fund Drawing," (Folder 1: 23)
  - "The Mechanism of the Forward Exchange Market,", 1961 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Book reviews, 1970-1991 (Folder 1: 25)
  - "Current Business Trends in Major Countries," speech, System Committee on Business Analysis, 1971 (Folder 1: 26)
  - "Devaluation-Bias and the Bretton Woods System,", 1972 (Folder 1: 27)
  - "Channels of Transmission of International Inflation," speech, Federal Reserve System Committee on International Research and Analysis, Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago, 1973 (Folder 1: 28)
  - "The Emerging Exchange-Rate System," speech, Banking Monetary and Fiscal Affairs Committee of the U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1973 (Folder 1: 29)
  - "'Imported Inflation' and Balance-of-Payments Adjustment,", 1973 (Folder 1: 30)
  - "Operations of Federal Reserve System," speech, School of Business and Public Administration, Howard University, 1973 (Folder 1: 31)
  - "The Par-Value System," Southern Economic and Finance Associations, Houston, Texas, 1973 (Folder 1: 32)
  - "The Emerging Exchange-Rate System (Early 1974)," (Folder 1: 33)
  - "Implications of Inflation for the International Monetary System," summary of presentation, 1974 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Speech, 1974 (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Monetary Picture in the European Community," speech, American Management Association, New York, 1975 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Request for permission for republication, 1975 (Folder 2: 4)
  - "World Economy: Some Considerations on the End of the Bretton Woods Era," speech, International Relations Roundtable, Georgetown University, 1975 (Folder 2: 5)
  - "International Economic Policies," speech, 1976 (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Monetarism and the Balance of Payments," speech, Ankara, Turkey, 1976 (Folder 2: 7)
  - U.S.-European Monetary Relations, monograph, edited by Katz, 1979 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Introductory remarks at German-American Forum, 1980 (Folder 2: 9)
  - "Continuity and Change in US Economic Policy," speech, SER-USICA Symposium, 1982 (Folder 2: 10)
  - "Thoughts On My Recent Trip to Four European Countries,", 1982 (Folder 2: 11)
  - "Commentary on Three Papers Presented to the Joint Session of the American Economic Association and American Finance Association on 'International Banking' in San Francisco, California,", 1983 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Statement before the Subcommittee on Commerce, Transportation and Tourism of the Committee on Energy and Commerce, United States House of Representatives, 1983 (Folder 2: 13)
  - "Will There Be a Crash of 1983?" speech, Dean's Office Seminar (Folder 2: 14)
  - "The Global Debt Problem: Entering Phase II," speech, Global Issues Seminar, 1984 (Folder 2: 15)
  - "Impact of Debt Crisis on Monetary System," summary written by Helen Lewis, 1984 (Folder 2: 16)
  - "International Cooperation and the LDC Debt Problem," speech, Global Issues Seminar, 1984 (Folder 2: 17)
  - "Some Thoughts on the Global Debt Problem," speech, National Economist Club, 1984 (Folder 2: 18)
  - "US Economic Policies and the World Economy," speech, Georgetown Leadership Seminar, 1984 (Folder 2: 19)
  - "Commentary on Professor Grubel's Paper on the Private Insurance of Bank Deposits," speech, Kiel Conference, 1985 (Folder 2: 20)
  - "Deregulation and Reregulation in U.S. Banking," speech, University of Berne, Switzerland, 1985 (Folder 2: 21)
  - "Exchange Rates and Intervention: The G-5 Accord," speech, Monetary Affairs Committee, Global Economic Action Institute, Milan, Italy, 1986 (Folder 2: 22)
  - "The Global Debt Crisis and International Banking Stability," speech, Diplomatic Academy, Vienna, Austria, 1986 (Folder 2: 23)
  - "The Rise and Fall of the Dollar," speech, Diplomatic Academy, Vienna, Austria, 1986 (Folder 2: 24)
  - "Can and Should the Current International Economic Order Survive to the Year 2000?" speech, Alumni Reunion, Georgetown Leadership Seminar, Hebrew University, Jerusalem, 1987 (Folder 2: 25)
  - "Determinants of Exchange Rates," speech, 1987 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Letter in response to comments on "Keynes and US Foreign Economic Policy,", 1987 (Folder 2: 27)
  - "The Twin Deficits: Interest Rates and the Dollar," speech, Baord of Directors of the DeVegh Fund, Washington, D.C., 1987 (Folder 2: 28)
  - "Trends in International Trade and foreign Investment," speech, Georgetown Leadership Seminar Alumni Conference, Templeton College, Oxford, England, 1988 (Folder 2: 29)
  - "The U.S. Budget Problem," Georgetown University, 1989 (Folder 2: 30)
  - "The Misaligned Dollar and World Payments Stability, 1980 to 1990," speech, Allied Social Sciences Annual Meeting, North American Finance and Economics Association and National Association of Business Economists, Washington, D.C. (Folder 2: 31)
  - "The Misaligned Dollar and World Payments Stability, 1980-1990," printed copy, 1991 (Folder 2: 32)
  - Statement by Katz, Colloquium in Honor of Sir Alexander Cairncross, Glasgow University, 1991 (Folder 2: 33)
  - The Legacy of the Golden Age, monograph, 1992 (Folder 2: 34)
    Includes contribution by Katz
- Career file, 1938-1993 (Box 3)
  Includes lecture outlines, correspondence, and research related to Katz's military service, teaching work, and a study conducted while Katz was an advisor to the Federal Reserve Board.
  - Course material, circa 1970-1988 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Federal Reserve Board, 1957-1958 (Folder 3: 2-3)
    Contains materials related to a study of the economic position of Great Britain. Includes letters of Kurt Eklof, W. J. Jackson, T. J. Lovell, W. Schwegler, and others
  - Georgetown University, 1982, undated (Folder 3: 4)
  - Georgetown University Bankers Forum, 1975-1993 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Military service, 1938-1992 (Folder 3: 6-7)
    Includes clipping of "Hitler Is Tops in Europe Writes Katz From London"
  - Speaking engagements, 1974-1975 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Tables of economic data, 1969 (Folder 3: 9)
- Printed matter, 1966-1994
  Includes monographs and articles on economics
  - 1966-1994 (Folder 3: 10-12)
- Oversize materials, 1940-1957 (Box 4)
  Contains academic diplomas, military citations, and a photograph
  - Diplomas, citations, and photographs, 1940-1957 (Box 4)